Register of the Alvin Kapusta collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Alvin Kapusta collection
1905-1986
87016
Hoover Institution Archives
36 manuscript boxes, 3 card file boxes, 3 envelopes (16.5 linear feet)
Clippings, photocopies of articles and pamphlets, photographs, notes, and bibliographies relating to Russian literature and art, especially in the emigration, and particularly to the writer Alekseĭ Remizov.
Kapusta, Alvin, collector.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1987.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content
This collection was assembled by Alvin Kapusta, a special assistant for Soviet nationalities in the U.S. State Department. He received his education at Minot State College and the University of California, Berkeley.
The collection consists of printed matter related to Russian and East European cultural and literary figures, to bibliographies of their work, and to bibliographical material in general. There is a detailed collection of printed matter related to the Russian author, Alekseĭ Remizov, including photocopies of his writings. Finally, there is a substantial amount of material dealing with the "Stundist" Movement in the Ukraine and the U.S., including accounts of religious persecution in the U.S.S.R.
The bulk of the collection covers the period from 1950-1980. The Alekseĭ Remizov material includes photocopies of books published from 1908-1955.
Remizov, Alekseĭ, 1877-1957.; Russian literature.; Art--Soviet Union.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.
- BIBLIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1914, undated (Boxes 1-4)
  Scope and Contents note
  Bibliographical material related to Russia and Eastern Europe. Includes bibliographical guides, and guides to libraries, archives, and printing houses dealing with Russian and East European material.
  - General
    - Librovich, S. F., Istoriia knigi v Rossii, 1914 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Preservation, Russian material (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - Russian literature, price lists (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Slavic archives outside the Soviet Union, arranged by country (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Slavic book (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Library of Congress. Alexis Babine Collection, miscellaneous material including correspondence (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Slavic books at the Library of Congress (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - Russian émigré
    - Bibliographical guide (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Book abroad (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Journals (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - Press (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Publishing houses in the West dealing with Russian material, arranged alphabetically (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Writers, arranged alphabetically
      - General (Box-folder 3: 2)
      - Poets (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - U.S.S.R.
    - Archives (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Collectors and collections (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
    - Libraries (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Library science (Box-folder 4: 2-3)
    - Soviet Republics
      Includes directories of periodicals, presses, and libraries both within the Soviet Union and in emigration.
      - Armenia (Box-folder 4: 4)
      - Belorussia (Box-folder 4: 5)
      - Georgia (Box-folder 4: 6)
      - Latvia (Box-folder 4: 7)
      - Lithuania (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - Moldavia (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - Turkistan (Box-folder 4: 10)
      - Soviet nationalities collections in the D.C. area (Box-folder 4: 11)
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1957-1980, undated (Boxes 4-16)
  Biographical material from periodical press re Russian cultural and literary figures, including dissident and Soviet writers.
  - Russian literary and cultural figures
    - General, 1957-1977 (Box-folder 4: 12-13)
      Includes biographical material, interviews, and book reviews from periodical press.
    - General, 1957-1977 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
    - A (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - B (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - C (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - D (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - E-F (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - G-I (Box-folder 6: 2)
    - K-L (Box-folder 6: 3)
    - M (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - N (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - O-P (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - R (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - S (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - T (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - U-W (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - Y (Box-folder 7: 5)
    - Z (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Dissidents and dissident writers, Soviet Union
    - General (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - A-M (Box-folder 8: 2)
    - N-Z (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - Amalrik, Andrei (Box-folder 8: 4-5)
    - Brodsky, Iosif (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - Daniel, IUlii, "Delo Andreia Siniavskogo i IUliia Daniela" (Box-folder 8: 7-9)
    - Daniel, IUlii, "Delo Andrea Siniavskogo i IUliia Daniela" (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Kuznetsov, Anatolii (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - Maksimov, Vladimir (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - Nekrasov, Victor (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - Siniavskii, Andrei [See also Daniel, IUlii above] (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - Solzhenitsyn, Aleksandr
      Clippings from Western press.
      - General (Box-folder 9: 6-7)
      - 1965-1969 (Box-folder 9: 8)
      - 1970-1974 (Box-folder 9: 9)
      - 1975-1976 (Box-folder 10: 1)
      - 1977-1980 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Russian émigré writers
    - General (Box-folder 10: 3-4)
    - A-R (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - S-Z (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - A (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - B (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - C-D (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - E (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - F (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - G (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - H-I (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - K (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - L-M (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - N-O (Box-folder 13: 2)
    - O-P (Box-folder 13: 3)
    - R-S (Box-folder 13: 4)
    - S (Box-folder 13: 5)
    - T (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - U-V (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - W-Z (Box-folder 14: 3)
    - Aldanov, Mark (Box-folder 14: 4)
    - Avterkhanov, A. (Box-folder 14: 5)
    - Bakhrakh, Aleksandr (Box-folder 14: 6)
    - Berezov, Rodion (Box-folder 14: 7)
    - Bunin, Ivan (Box-folder 14: 8)
    - Elagin, Ivan (Box-folder 14: 9)
    - Fesenko, Tat'iana (Box-folder 14: 10)
    - Filippov, Boris (Box-folder 14: 11)
    - Gul', Roman (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - Ivask, IUrii (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Khodasevich, V. (Box-folder 15: 3)
    - Klenovskii, Dmitrii (Box-folder 15: 4)
    - Koriakov, Mikhail (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - Kuprin, Aleksandr (Box-folder 15: 6)
    - Levitskii, Sergei (Box-folder 15: 7)
    - Meier, IUrii (Box-folder 15: 8)
    - Merezhkovskii, Dmitrii (Box-folder 15: 9)
    - Nabokov, Vladimir (Box-folder 15: 10)
    - Ossorgin, M. (Box-folder 15: 11)
    - Polchaninov, R. (Box-folder 15: 12)
    - Pushkarev, S. (Box-folder 15: 13)
    - Rafal'skii, S. (Box-folder 15: 14)
    - Rzhevskii, Leonid (Box-folder 15: 15)
    - Sedykh, Andrei (Box-folder 15: 16)
    - Shakhovskoi, Archbishop Ioann (Box-folder 15: 17)
    - Shmelev, Ivan (Box-folder 15: 18)
    - Struve, Gleb (Box-folder 15: 19)
    - Teffi (Box-folder 15: 20)
    - Terapiano, IUrii (Box-folder 15: 21)
    - Tsvetaeva, Marina (Box-folder 15: 22)
    - Weidle, Vladimir (Box-folder 15: 23)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii (Box-folder 15: 24)
    - Zaitsev, Boris (Box-folder 15: 25)
  - Third emigration
    Clippings from periodical press, arranged alphabetically.
    - A-K (Box-folder 16: 1)
    - L-Z (Box-folder 16: 2)
- ALEKSEI REMIZOV FILE, 1905-1955, undated (Boxes 16-31)
  Bibliographical and biographical material re Alekseĭ Remizov, photocopies and translations of his writings, critical works re Remizov, and miscellaneous material related to Alvin Kapusta's study of this writer.
  - General archive (Box-folder 16: 3-5)
    Includes photocopies of correspondence, bibliographical, biographical, and critical material and writings by the author.
  - General archive (Box-folder 17: 1-5)
  - General archive (Box-folder 18: 1-2)
  - Bibliography
    - General (Box-folder 18: 3-5)
    - General (Box-folder 19: 1-6)
    - General (Box-folder 20: 1-6)
    - Minor works (Box-folder 21: 1-4)
    - Major works (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - Photocopies of published works
    - Akhru. Povest' peterburgskaia, 1922 (Box-folder 22: 1)
    - Bezpriiutnaia, 1922 (Box-folder 22: 2)
    - Chasy, 1908 (Box-folder 22: 3)
    - Chortov log i polunoshchnoe solntse. Razskazy i poemy, 1908 (Box-folder 22: 4-5)
    - Chto est' tabak, undated (Box-folder 22: 6)
    - Dokuka i balagur'e, 1914 (Box-folder 22: 7)
    - E. Tibetskii skaz, 1922 (Box-folder 22: 8)
    - Golubinaia kniga, 1946 (Box-folder 22: 9)
    - Koriavka, 1922 (Box-folder 22: 10)
    - Kukkha. Rozanovy pis'ma, 1923 (Box-folder 22: 11)
    - Lalazar. Kavkazskii skaz, 1922 (Box-folder 22: 12)
    - Limonad. Sirech': put' dukhovnyi, 1907 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - Meliuzina Bruntsvik, 1952 (Box-folder 23: 2)
    - Myshkina dudochka, 1953 (Box-folder 23: 3)
    - Nikola milostivyi, 1918 (Box-folder 23: 4)
    - Nikoliny pritchi, undated (Box-folder 23: 5)
    - O Iude printse Iskariotskom, 1908 (Box-folder 23: 6)
    - O sud'be ognenoi, undated (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - Ognenaia Rossiia, undated (Box-folder 23: 8)
    - Ogon' veshchii. Sny i predson'e, 1954 (Box-folder 23: 9)
    - Podorozh'e, 1913 (Box-folder 23: 10)
    - Posolon, 1906 (Box-folder 23: 11)
    - Povest' o Ivane Semenoviche Stratilatove, 1922 (Box-folder 23: 12)
    - Prud, 1908
      - Part I (Box-folder 24: 1)
      - Part II (Box-folder 24: 2)
    - Razskazy, 1910 (Box-folder 24: 3)
    - Rusaliia, 1923 (Box-folder 23: 4)
    - Russkiia zapiski, 1939 July (Box-folder 23: 5)
    - Skazki obez'ian'iago tsaria Asyki, undated (Box-folder 23: 6)
    - Skazki Russkago Naroda skazannyia Alekseem Remizovym, 1923 (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - Sobach'ia dolia, 1922 (Box-folder 23: 8)
    - Snezhok, 1918 (Box-folder 23: 9)
    - Strannitsa. Povest', 1918 (Box-folder 23: 10)
    - Tri serpa, 1929 (Box-folder 25: 1)
    - Tsar' Dodon, 1921 (Box-folder 25: 2)
    - Tsar' Maksimilian, 1920 (Box-folder 25: 3)
    - Ukrepa, 1916 (Box-folder 25: 4)
    - V pole blakitnom, 1922 (Box-folder 25: 5)
    - Vesennee porosh'e, 1915 (Box-folder 25: 6)
    - Za sviatuiu Rus'. Dumy o rodnoi zemle, 1915 (Box-folder 25: 7)
    - Zavetnye skazki, undated (Box-folder 25: 8)
    - Miscellaneous short work, 1905-1955 (Box-folder 25: 9)
  - Biographical material (Box-folder 25: 10)
  - Reminiscences about Remizov (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - Correspondence (Box-folder 26: 2)
  - Criticism
    - Bibliography of critical material (Box-folder 26: 3)
    - Rysten'ko, A. V., Zametki o sochineniiakh Alekseia Remizova, 1913 (Box-folder 26: 4)
    - Soviet (Box-folder 26: 5)
    - A (Box-folder 26: 6)
    - B-C (Box-folder 27: 1)
    - D-G (Box-folder 27: 2)
    - H-I (Box-folder 27: 3)
    - J-K (Box-folder 27: 4)
    - L-R (Box-folder 27: 5)
    - S (Box-folder 28: 1)
    - T-X (Box-folder 28: 2)
    - Y-Z (Box-folder 28: 3)
  - Translations of his work
    - General (Box-folder 28: 4-5)
    - For translation (Box-folder 28: 6)
    - Ou finit l'escalier (Box-folder 29: 1)
  - Visual material
    - Drawings and calligraphy, critical material (Box-folder 29: 2)
    - Photocopies of drawings for frontispieces (Box-folder 29: 3)
    - Images of Aleksei Remizov, drawings and handwritten and illustrated albums from Thomas P. Whitney Collection (Box-folder 29: 4)
  - Kapusta, Alvin
    Miscellaneous material related to his study of Remizov.
    - General (Box-folder 29: 5-6)
    - General (Box-folder 30: 1)
    - Correspondence re Remizov, arranged alphabetically (Box-folder 30: 2)
    - Book search, want lists (Box-folder 30: 3)
    - Work file (Box-folder 30: 4)
    - Working folder (Box-folder 30: 5)
    - Work plans and preparations (Box-folder 31: 1)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1951-1983, undated (Boxes 31-35)
  General material related to Eastern Europe and the U.S.S.R., including history, religion, nationalism, and dissident movements.
  - Bulgaria (Box-folder 31: 2)
  - Central Asia (Box-folder 31: 3-7)
  - Central Asia (Box-folder 32: 1)
  - Czechoslovakia (Box-folder 32: 2)
  - Ethnic organizations, 1975-1983 (Box-folder 32: 3)
    Includes guides and directories.
  - Poland (Box-folder 32: 4)
  - Religion
    - Baptists in the U.S.S.R., material related to persecution
      - Amnesty International, bulletins and correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 32: 5)
      - International Representation for the Council of Evangelical Baptist Churches of the Soviet Union Inc., bulletins, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 32: 6)
      - "Biulleten' soveta rodstvennikov uznikov evangel'skikh khristian-baptistov v S.S.S.R."
        - No. 24 (Box-folder 32: 7)
        - No. 37 (Box-folder 32: 8)
        - No. 38 (Box-folder 32: 9)
        - No. 39 (Box-folder 32: 10)
        - No. 40 (Box-folder 32: 11)
        - No. 41 (Box-folder 32: 12)
        - No. 42 (Box-folder 32: 13)
        - No. 51 (Box-folder 32: 14)
    - Khristiianskii visnik, printed copies, 1951-1958, 1983 (Box-folder 33: 1)
    - Unofficial religious publications (Box-folder 33: 2)
    - "Stundism"
      - General (Box-folder 33: 3)
      - History (Box-folder 33: 4-5)
  - Russian emigres. General (Box-folder 33: 6)
  - Russian emigres. General (Box-folder 34: 1)
  - Vozrozhdenie, miscellaneous photocopies (Box-folder 34: 2)
  - Ukraine
    - Bibliographical material (Box-folder 34: 3)
    - History (Box-folder 34: 4)
    - Miscellaneous printed matter (Box-folder 34: 5)
  - U.S.S.R.
    - General (Box-folder 34: 6)
    - Art (Box-folder 34: 7)
    - History (Box-folder 35: 1)
    - Human rights (Box-folder 35: 2)
    - Literature (Box-folder 35: 3-5)
    - Nationalism (Box-folder 35: 6)
  - Yugoslavia
    - Dissidents, biographical material (Box-folder 35: 7)
    - Mihajlov, Mihajlo (Box-folder 35: 8)
- ALVIN KAPUSTA WRITINGS, 1983, undated (Box 36)
  Typescripts and photocopies of Alvin Kapusta's writings. Typescript copies unless otherwise indicated.
  - "East Slavic Genealogy" (Box-folder 36: 1)
  - "The First Slavonic Bible, 1581 and Ivan Fedorov" (Box-folder 36: 2)
  - "75th Anniversary First Baptist Church, Max, North Dakota", printed copies, 1983 (Box-folder 36: 3)
  - "Soviet Nationalities: Archives in a Submerged Nation. The Case of the Ukraine" (Box-folder 36: 4)
  - "The State Records of Today's Superpowers: How the U.S. and the U.S.S.R. Manage Their National Archival Heritage" (Box-folder 36: 5)
- INDEX CARD FILE, undated (Boxes 37-39)
  Material on Russian and East European bibliography and literature.
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, undated (Photo file)
  Photographs of Russian and East European writers, cultural figures, and dissidents.
  - 14 prints related to Maksimilian Voloshin, undated (Envelope A)
    Includes 4 prints of Voloshin, 2 of his wife, 1 of his father, and 1 of himself and his mother.
  - 42 prints of Ukrainian dissidents, undated (Envelope B)
    Includes 3 prints of Viacheslav Chornovil, 2 prints of Ivan Dziuba, and 2 prints of Valentin Moroz.
  - 9 miscellaneous prints, undated (Envelope C)
    Includes Russian writers and Ukrainian dissidents.